现在让我们学习
Let's now learn
关于所谓的伪类。
about something called pseudo classes.
现在，伪类听起来很奇怪，
Now, pseudo class sounds very strange,
但它实际上非常简单。
but it's actually pretty straightforward.
作为一个例子，
And as an example,
让我们尝试为第一个列表元素设置样式
let's try to style the first list elements
不同于其他的。
different from the other ones.
所以我们有这个列表和这个列表。
So we have this list here and this list.
所以，正如我刚才所说，
And so, as I just said,
让我们尝试设置第一个元素的样式
let's try to style the first element
每个列表的不同。
of each of the lists differently.
例如，通过使它们加粗。
for example, by making them bold.
所以这个元素和这个元素
So this element and this element
现在直截了当
now the straightforward way
这样做就是为每个人添加一个类
of doing this would be to add a class to each of them
然后为它们设计样式。
and then style them.
对？
Right?
因此，让我们实际尝试第一个示例。
So let's actually try that first example.
所以这里有一份清单。
So here is one list.
所以让我们添加一个类
So let's add a class of
第一的
first
李，
li,
然后让我们做同样的事情
and then let's do the same
到我们在这里的其他列表。
to the other lists that we have up here.
然后回到或CSS，
And then back in or CSS,
让我们选择第一个 li 类的所有元素。
let's select all the elements with the first li class.
然后记得使文本加粗。
And then remember to make text bold.
我们使用字体粗细
We use font-weight
设置为粗体，
set to bold,
事实上，我们在这里。
and indeed, here we are.
所以现在这个是大胆的，这个，
So now this one is bold and this one,
但我们实际上可以做得比这更好。
but we can actually do better than this.
因此，与其手动执行此操作，
So instead of doing this manually,
我们实际上可以让 CSS 自动计算出来，
we can actually have CSS automatically figure out,
这是容器内的第一个 li 元素。
which is the first li element inside of a container.
所以让我们真正做到这一点，我仍然会保持
So let's actually do that and I will still keep
HTML 中的类，只是为了让我们将其作为参考，
the classes in the HTML, just so we keep it as a reference,
但现在让我向您展示我们实际上如何才能做得更好。
but now let me show you how we can actually do it better.
所以我们从使用 li 开始，
So we start by using li,
这将基本上选择所有 li 元素，
which will basically select all the li elements,
但是我们使用了一个伪类
but then we use a pseudo class
我们开始一个伪类
and we start a pseudo class
通过写一个冒号
by writing a colon
像这样。
like this.
然后是我们感兴趣的一个
And then to one that we're interested in here
被首先调用
is called first
冲刺孩子。
dash child.
就是这样。
And that's it.
现在在这里，我们可以说字体粗细并将其设置为粗体。
And now here, we can say font weight and set it to bold.
那么让我们看看。
So let's see.
事实上，它现在起作用了，他们又恢复了大胆。
And indeed it worked now they are back to being bold.
所以我们基本上在这里改变了我们的选择器
So we basically changed our selector here
并为其添加了一个伪类。
and added a pseudo class to it.
这个第一个子伪类做了什么
And what this first child pseudo class does
是它会选择一个li元素，
is that it will select an li element,
或者实际上是选择了所有 li 元素
or actually it was select all the li elements that are
其父元素的第一个子元素。
the first child elements of its parent elements.
所以这正是这里和这里的情况。
And so that is exactly the case right here and right here.
对？
Right?
所以这里的这个 li 元素
So this li element here
是其父元素的第一个子元素。
is the first-child element of its parent.
所以在这种情况下，Ol 元素，
So in this case, the Ol element,
因此这个选择器
and therefore this selector
我们在这里写的将针对该元素。
that we wrote here will target that element.
完全相同的事情也是
And the exact same thing is too
对于此处的其他列表。
for this other list down here.
好的。
Okay.
所以让我们再试一次，李。
So let's try another one again, li.
然后我们还有一个叫做last-child。
and then we also have one called the last-child.
直到让它变成斜体，
Until lets make it italic,
所以字体样式
so font style
并将其设置为斜体。
and set it to a italic.
事实上，现在最后一个变成了斜体。
And indeed, now the last one became italic.
所以两者都在这里
So both here
都在这里
and both here
因为再次，
because again,
它们都是 li 元素，现在是最后一个孩子
both of them are li elements that are now the last-child
在其父容器内。
inside of its parent container.
接下来，我们实际上还可以针对特定的孩子。
Next up, we can actually also target a specific child.
例如，第三个或第二个孩子。
So for example, the third or the second child.
所以为此，我们使用 nth-child 伪类，
So for that, we use the nth-child pseudo class,
然后在这里我们实际上需要写括号
and then here we actually need to write parenthesis
这样我们就可以指定我们想要哪个孩子。
like this so we can specify which of the child that we want.
所以假设我们想要第二个孩子
So let's say we want the second child
有一种颜色
to have a color of
红色的。
red.
所以在这里只使用一个编码的颜色名称，
So using just a coded color name here,
让我们来看看。
let's see.
确实在这里。
And indeed here it is.
或者如果我们尝试第三个，
Or if we tried the third one,
那么确实是这里的第三个
then indeed it would be the third one here
和这里也是如此。
and here as well.
甚至比这更好，
And even better than that,
是我们实际上可以在这里使用一些关键字。
is that we can actually use some keywords here.
所以我们可以写奇数。
so we can write odd.
现在所有奇怪的元素都会变成红色。
And now all the odd elements will be red.
所以第一个元素，然后是第二个元素，
So element number one, then number two,
或者实际上是第三个，这里是第一个元素，
or actually number three, and here it's element number one,
第三，第五。
number three, and number five.
如果还有更多，
And if there were more,
然后它会选择数字七，九，十一
then it would select number seven, nine, eleven
等等等等。
and so on and so forth.
当然，如果我们能做些奇怪的事，
And of course, if we can do odd,
那么我们也可以做到
then we can also do even
这样我们就可以选择第二个，
so that we'll then select a number two,
四、六、八
four, six, eight
等等等等。
and so on and so forth.
所以你看到第二个
So you see number two
这里是两个和四个。
and here two and four.
对？
Right?
所以这个技术非常有用
So this technique is quite useful
例如，为表格设置样式，
for example, to style tables,
这通常具有交替的背景颜色。
which oftentimes have like alternating background colors.
所以我相信你已经在某个地方看到过。
So I'm sure you have seen that somewhere.
因此，这里的这种技术非常有帮助。
And so it's very helpful for that this technique here.
现在让我们在这里实际注释掉这个属性
Now let's actually comment out this property here
因为我们不希望这里的文字是红色的
because we don't want or text here to be red
实际上在最后一页。
actually in a final page.
好的，所以这只是为了向您展示
Alright, So this was just to show you
我们可以在这里做的一切。
everything that we can do here.
最后，让我澄清一个常见的误解
Now finally, let me clear up a common misconception
周围有伪类。
that there is around the pseudo classes.
所以假设我们想要选择
So let's say that we wanted to select
文章内部的第一个段落元素。
the first paragraph element that's inside of the article.
所以让我们在我们的标记中检查一下。
So let's check that out here in our markup.
所以在文章里面，
So inside of the article,
第一段基本上就是这个。
the first paragraph would basically be this one here.
对？
Right?
所以让我们看看我们可以在这里做什么。
So let's see what we can do here.
所以我刚才说的
So what I just said
基本上是
is basically
文章然后p。
article and then p.
这就是后代选择器。
so that's the descendant selector.
对？
Right?
所以选择文章内部的段落
So selecting a paragraph that's inside of the article
现在选择第一个。
and now selecting the very first of that.
所以是第一个孩子。
So first-child.
现在假设我们想要颜色。
And now let's say we want the color.
要在这件事情上红起来，
To be red in this one,
但是当我们重新加载并查看我们的页面时，
but as we reload this and check out our page,
你看什么都没发生。
you see that nothing happened.
所以实际上没有段落变红。
So no paragraph actually turned red.
再一次，误解是这里的选择器
So again, the misconception is that this selector here
应该选择第一个 p 元素
should have selected the first p element
文章里面。
inside of the article.
所以这就是这个。
And so this would be this one.
对？
Right?
所以正如我们在本段之前看到的那样ct,
So as we just saw before this paragraph is in fact,
然而，文章内的第一段，
the first paragraph inside of the article however,
这不是第一个子伪类的实际工作方式。
this is not how the first child pseudo class actually works.
相反，CSS 会选择一个 p 元素
Instead, what CSS will do is to select a p element
那实际上是文章的第一个孩子。
that is actually the first child of the article.
好的？
Alright?
所以p元素是第一个p元素
So the p element is the first p element
文章里面，
inside of the article,
但它不是文章的第一个孩子。
but it is not the first child of article.
文章的第一个孩子实际上是标题。
The first child of article is actually header.
对？
Right?
它不是一个段落。
It is not a paragraph.
因此，这里的选择器在某种程度上不起作用
And so therefore this selector here does not work in a way
也许我们会认为它会。
that maybe we might think it would.
所以这只适用于段落，
So this would only work if a paragraph,
实际上是文章的第一个元素。
would actually be to first element of the article.
所以让我们这样做。
So let's do that.
因此，如果我们现在保存，那么我们确实会得到一些红色段落。
So if we save now then indeed we get some red paragraph.
所以现在这一段是文章的第一个孩子。
So now this paragraph is the first-child of the article.
因此，现在我们的选择器适用。
And so therefore now our selector applies.
好的？
Alright?
现在让我们看看我们文章的结尾。
now let's see the end of our article.
所以到此结束
So it ends here
我们可以看到一个段落实际上是
and we can see that a paragraph is actually
article 元素的最后一个子元素。
the last-child of the article element.
对？
Right?
所以这会起作用。
And so what would work is this.
那么让我们看看我们的结果。
So let's see our result.
事实上，现在这个文本是红色的。
And indeed, now this text is the red.
所以这是有道理的。
And so it makes sense.
对？
Right?
这再次奏效
Again this worked
因为是文章里面的一个p元素
because it is a p element inside of the article
它确实是那篇文章的最后一个孩子。
and it is indeed the last-child of that article.
因此，然后应用了这个选择器
And so therefore this selector then applied
并做了它应该做的事情。
and did exactly what it should do.
所以基本上这意味着
So basically what this means is that
当我们在父元素中混合多个元素时，
when we mix multiple elements inside of a parent element,
那么伪类就不能很好地工作。
then the pseudo classes don't work really well.
然而，它们非常适合这种情况，
They are however perfect for situations like this one,
其中所有子元素都相同。
where all the child elements are the same.
所以在像 ul 或 ol 这样的列表中，所有子元素
So in a list like ul or ol all the child elements
应该是 li ，所以 dos 伪类，
are supposed to be li and so the does pseudo class,
像第一个孩子，最后一个孩子或第n个孩子一样完美。
like first-child, last-child or nth-child work perfectly.
好的。
Alright.
这就是您使用这些伪类的方式。
And this is how you work with these pseudo classes.
现在，我们刚刚学习的伪类
Now, the pseudo classes that we just learned about
都是为了匹配现有的 HTML 结构。
are all about matching the existing HTML structure.
但是，还有其他类型的伪类。
However, there are also other types of pseudo classes.
所以让我们在下一个视频中使用其中的一些
And so let's use some of them in the next video
最终样式或超链接。
to finally style or hyperlinks.